<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Installing Naked Objects</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>To develop or run Naked Objects applications you need Java version
    1.5 or above installed on your machine.</para>

    <para>To run the examples you will also need Ant installed. <ulink
    url="http://ant.apache.org/">Ant</ulink> is available from Apache. As an
    alternative to Ant you may build an application using <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</ulink>, which is also available from
    Apache.</para>

    <para>To develop applications you will need a suitable development
    environment. If you have the choice, we recommend using <ulink
    url="www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</ulink>, because there are some specific
    plug-ins available for Eclipse to facilitate developing with Naked
    Objects. However, Naked Objects may be used with any IDE, or even just the
    JDK.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Downloading the framework</title>

    <para>The latest version of the Naked Objects framework can be downloaded
    from the downloads page of the <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/nakedobjects/">Naked Objects
    Sourceforge project</ulink> as shown below. You may download either the
    binary release (suffixed with '-bin' ) for immediate use, the full source
    release (suffixed with '-source' ) if you wish to build the framework
    yourself, or simply a jar file that bundles in all the dependencies but
    has no documentation or other resources.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="40%" fileref="images/downloads.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Naked Objects</title>

    <para>Extract the downloaded file's content into a suitable directory (a
    root directory is created upon extraction so there is no need to create a
    directory in which to install everything).</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Binary release</title>

      <para>The binary release provides the following directories and
      files:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a set of jar files making up the Naked Objects framework, and
          other third party jars required by the framework (in <filename
          class="directory" moreinfo="none">lib/</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>one or more demo applications that may be run from the command
          line (in <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">demos/</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>one or more example applications that may be edited, compiled
          and run via Ant (in <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">examples/</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>documentation (in <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">docs/</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>a <filename class="directory"
          moreinfo="none">resource</filename> directory with icon images and
          templates</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Source release</title>

      <para>The source release contains a series of directories, which are
      Eclipse projects, for the different subcomponents of Naked Objects, the
      libs and examples. This source can be used, with the templates in the
      build directories, to recreate the distributions made publicly
      available.</para>

      <para>To install all the components into your local repository, and
      generate the distribution files, use the install goal twice in Maven as
      below:</para>

      <screen>&gt; cd nakedobjects-3.0.1 &gt; mvn clean install &gt; mvn clean
      install -P dist</screen>

      <para>Any missing resources that maven complains about are can be
      installed into the repository by specifying the specific jar file from
      the lib directory when following the instructions that Maven gives
      you.</para>

      <para>Using the source release Maven will build the same files that you
      would download if you had downloaded a binary version. The distribution
      files (as detailed for the binary release above) are to be found within
      the directory <filename class="directory"
      moreinfo="none">distribution/tarball/target</filename> as shown
      below.</para>

      <screen>distribution tarball target nakedobjects-3.0.1-bin.tar.gz
      nakedobjects-3.0.1-bin.zip nakedobjects-3.0.1-source.zip
      nakedobjects-3.0.1-with-dependencies.jar </screen>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
